The voice you hear
is not my speaking voice
but my mind's voice.
I have not spoken
since I was six years old.
No-one knows why.
Not even me.
Come on!
My father says
it is a dark talent,
and the day I take it
into my head to stop breathing
will be my last.
Today he married me to a man
I've not yet met.
Soon my daughter and I shall
join him in his own country.
My husband said my muteness
does not bother him.
He writes - and hark this -
God loves dumb creatures,
so why not he?
Were good
he had God's patience...
...for silence affects everyone
in the end.
The strange thing is
I don't think myself silent.
That is because of my piano.
I shall miss it on the journey.
Give me your hand.
Come on!
You're with me!
I've got the lady.
Easy! It's Sunday.
There you go.
Watch it!
There you are, madam.
Paddington Station.
Over here, me lovely.
Alright, lads. Unbutton.
I could piss like a toff.
Get that boat unloaded.
Come on! First!
The six whole months
I spent in Dublin...
Jesus Christ!
Whose bloody coffin is this?!
Christ, it's heavy!
Hold it!
Yes, yes. Big coffin, this is!
Fuck them.
We'll just leave 'em behind.
It's what they fuckin' want.
A pox on you!
Oh, I like that! Very good.
Leave 'em and be lynched for
the pleasure. That is sweet.
It's a bit rough out there.
Could be they can't get through
to you in this weather.
Do you have things for shelter?
She says thank you.
Does your mother prefer
to come on with us to Nelson?
She says no.
She says she would rather be
boiled alive by natives
than get back on your
stinkin' tub.
You be damn fortuned
I don't smack your puppy gob,
young missy!
Damn lucky!
We're all ready now, sir.
Mother, watch out!
Oh, hell! Are they alright?
Here.
Look. I'm a very big moth.
Will it catch fire?
I'm not gonna call him 'Papa'.
I'm not gonna call him
anything.
I'm not even gonna look at him.
Are we stopping?
Shall we stop?
We must get on.
Miss McGrath?
Alisdair Stewart.
You'll have to wake yourself.
I've got men here
to carry your things.
Well, I see you've got
a good many boxes.
I'd like to know
what's in each...
Can you hear me?!
Oh, well, that's good.
Yes, that's good.
What's in this one?
You're small.
I never thought you'd be small.
And... and this one?
Very large.
What's in it, then? A bedstead?
It's my mother's piano.
Baines, tell them
to carry in pairs.
Take all the boxes...
...the table, and, uh...
...the suitcases.
What do you think?
She looks tired.
She's stunted.
That's one thing.
The big crate?
No, no.
Just the trunks and the boxes,
as I explained.
No, no. It can't come now.
It must.
She wants it to come.
Yes, and so do I,
but there are too few of us
here to carry it now.
Too heavy.
Do you mean you don't
want your clothing
or your kitchenware to come?
Is that what you mean?
We can't leave the piano!
Look, let's not discuss
this any further.
I'm very pleased
that you arrived safely...
Mother wants to know
if they could come back
directly for it.
Could I apologise for the
delay, which I regret was...
After they've taken
the other things.
Might I suggest
that you prepare yourself
for a difficult journey?
The bush will tear clothing and
the mud is very deep in places.
Hey, Stewart!
What do they think
they're doing?
We don't have time for this!
Baines!
What's the matter?
Why are they stopping?
That's the way to
the burial ground. It's tap...
But we came down this way.
I'm sure we did.
They want more money.
That's all it is.
They're trying to make
two days out of it.
No.
No, they know another track -
to the side of this.
Septimus! Now, take that off!
Take that off!
Watch your feet!
Oh, watch your feet!
Stop, Septimus! Please stop it!
Stop it!
Oh, Septimus, stop it, please.
Oh, you'll tear it!
Oh, the tag's broken.
Septimus, now stop it.
Oh, you'll tear it! Be careful!
Arm down.
If you cannot have
a ceremony together,
you have at least a photograph.
Careful. The lace
is most fragile.
My real father was
a famous German composer.
They met when my mother was
an opera singer in Luxembourg.
Why?
I want to be in the photograph.
Will we leave the cloth
here for the photograph?
No, no. It is just
to keep the chair dry.
Ah, here they are.
How beautiful.
I almost slipped
on the planks, Uncle.
They've gotten very greasy.
Aye, you use the left chair.
Pull the tarpaulin.
I am sorry for the rain.
Pity I'm not lighted up inside.
Shower for
a spring... for a spring bride.
Shall I hold the umbrella
on this side, or t'other?
On t'other, on t'other.
Move over!
Can you take this, please?
And... sitting!
Uh... very still.
And where did they get married?
In an enormous forest, with
real fairies as bridesmaids,
each holding
a little elf's hand.
No. I tell a lie.
It was in a small country
church in the mountains.
Which mountains
are those, dear?
The Pyrenees.
I've never been there.
Mother used to sing
the songs in German,
and her voice would echo
across the valleys.
That was before the accident.
And what happened?
One day,
when my mother and father
were singing together
in the forest,
a great storm blew up
out of nowhere.
But so passionate
was their singing
that they did not notice,
nor did they stop
as the rain began to fall.
And when their voices rose
for the final bars of the duet,
a great bolt of lightning...
...came out of the sky
and struck my father
so that he lit up like a torch.
And at the same moment
my father was struck dead,
my mother was struck dumb!
She never spoke another word.
Oh, dear.
Not another word?
Oh, from the shock, yes.
It would be.
Terrible. Terrible.
Oh, dear!
Oh! Terrible.
Terrible.
There, there, d...
Dear!
I'm sorry.
I have to go away
for some days.
There's some Maori land
I'm interested in
which I... may buy
very reasonably.
Well, I hope you'll spend
the time to get settled in
and perhaps... in some ways...
...we could start again.
Alright?
I'm not able to read.
Please take us back to
the beach where we landed.
I am sorry. I can't do that.
I don't have the time.
Goodbye.
I can't take you there.
I can't do it.
Mumma! Mumma!
Watch me! Watch!
Hello there.
Hello.
Well, you've stopped
combing your hair,
which is a good thing.
It was looking overdone.
You see, these are the slits
that the heads will go through.
Show him, Nessie.
Slits.
They'll be dead. The reverend's
going to use animal blood.
No doubt it'll be
very dramatic.
Be very dramatic.
Tea!
Morag...
...what would you think
if someone...
were to play a kitchen table...
...like it were a piano?
Like it were a piano?
Yes. It's strange, isn't it?
I mean, it's not a piano.
It's...
It doesn't make any sound.
Biscuits!
- No. No sound.
- I mean...
...I knew she was mute, but...
...now I'm thinking
perhaps it's more than that.
I'm wondering if she's not...
...brain-affected.
Shush!
No sound at all?
Well, no. It was a table.
Well, she was very violent
with the gown.
She tore off a chunk of lace.
If I hadn't been there
to see it,
I'd have sworn she'd have
used her teeth and...
Wiped her feet on it.
Well, it hasn't come
to anything yet. It's...
...simply a concern, that's all.
Yes.
Yes, of course, a concern.
There's something to be said
for silence.
Indeed.
Cotton!
And, with time,
I'm sure she'll become...
...affectionate.
Certainly there's nothing
so easy to like as a pet,
and they're quite silent.
Those 80 acres
across the stream.
What do you think of them?
I don't have any money.
What are you on about?
I'd like to make a swap.
What for?
The piano.
What, the piano on the beach?
It's not marshy, is it?
No.
Well, Baines the music lover.
I never would have thought.
Hidden talents, George?
I'd have to get lessons.
It wouldn't be much use
without them.
Oh, yes, I suppose you would.
Well, Ada can play.
I have in a letter
that she plays very well.
She's been playing
since she was five or six.
What on?
Well, on your piano.
That's the swap.
What'd she say?
She says it's her piano and
she won't have him touch it!
He's an oaf. He can't read.
He's ignorant.
Well, he wants
to improve himself.
And you'll be able to play it.
Teach him how to look after it!
You can't go on like this.
We're a family now. We all make
sacrifices and so will you!
You will teach him.
And I will see to it!
Ah! A Broadwood.
Oh, a fine instrument.
I've not seen one here.
Nor in New South Wales,
where I've tuned some 200.
Yes, they like
their pianos there.
Scent.
And salt, of course.
Mother says she can't stand
to teach piano
with it all out of tune,
so I'm to do scales.
I hope you scrubbed your hands.
Ooh. It's in tune.
It's in tune!
I was teaching!
Mother would like to see
what you can play.
I'd rather... not play.
I want to listen
and learn that way.
Everyone has to practise.
I just want to listen.
Lovely.
Oh, but tell me again!
Was he a teacher?
How did you speak to him?
What happened?
Why didn't you get married?
Shall I kiss you goodnight?
Get out! You need a bath!
Go on! Out! Bad dog!
Boo! Go on, you're dirty!
Bad, smelly dog!
Move it, Flynn!
Ada, wait. Wait.
Do you know how... to bargain?
There's a way you can have
your piano back.
Do you want it back?
You see...
...I'd like us to make a deal.
There's... things I'd...
...like to do while you play.
If you let me,
you can earn it back.
What do you think?
One visit for every key.
Your dress?
Skirt?
For every black one?
That's a lot less. Half.
Alright. Alright.
Then the black keys.
Poor baby.
What horrid little person
put you in the rain
and shoved you with a stick?
Hmm, baby? Hmm?
You're alright with moi.
Scissors.
Thank you.
Nessie, put that down and
come and put your hand out.
Oh, no. Please, Mr Stewart...
No, no, no.
Nessie, please.
Go on, Nessie.
She's timid.
Alright, Mary, come along.
Down here.
Well, come on, girl!
Get a move on!
Oh! Alright, then.
Down here. Put out your hand.
Now...
No, no. Put out your hand here.
No, no. Look, look.
You're being attacked.
No. Come on, come on.
There you go.
And with the blood,
it will be a very good effect.
Here, Flynn. Here, Flynn.
Here, Flynn. Flynn! Flynn!
Flynn! Here, Flynn.
Bad boy. Here, wee boy.
Bad, bad boy.
Flynn!
Flynn, don't be trouble.
Flynn! Flynn.
I want to speak to my mother.
I don't want to be outside.
I want to watch.
I'll be very quiet.
I won't look at him.
- Be very careful.
- Careful.
I hardly need to give one to
you, but here you are anyway.
Don't be late.
You will see
that there are two times,
and since you are
accompanying a performer,
you will need to make
the earlier time.
Wait!
How are the lessons going?
He's getting on alright,
then, is he?
She seems quietened down.
Is she more affectionate?
Oh, well.
Slowly. Slowly.
Lift your skirt.
Lift it higher.
Higher.
Higher!
Lift it higher.
You no worry, Baine.
I save you.
I have a wife.
I save her too.
Where's your wife?
My wife?
Oh, she has a life of her own.
In Hull, England.
Must be ugly
for you to run away.
You need another wife.
Undo your dress.
I want to see your arms.
Play.
Two keys.
"I shall listen hard
at rehearsal
"because I live too far
to come often."
Which sign is the word
'rehearsal'?
I can't imagine a fate
worse than being dumb.
To be deaf.
Oh, aye. Deaf too.
Terrible. Awful.
Actually, to tell you
the whole truth,
Mother says most people
speak rubbish
and it's not worth the listen.
Well, that is a strong opinion.
Aye. It's unholy.
What do they say?
Are they selling?
Offer the blankets
for half the land.
12.
The guns, Baines.
Offer the guns.
What do they want the land for?
They don't do anything with it.
They don't cultivate it, they
don't burn it back, nothing.
I mean, how do they even know
that it's theirs?
I thought I might as well mark
it out, you know? As we agreed.
Yes. Why not?
Well, Ada says you're doing
well with the piano.
I'll have to come
and hear you play.
What do you play?
Nothing just yet.
No?
Ada, four keys.
Why five?
I just want to lie.
Alright. Alright. Five.
Take it easy.
Here, mind that hole now.
Steady.
Hang on. Alright. There you go.
How are you, then? So, will you
marry me next week?
Just put your arm around me.
That's right, love.
That's the way.
Oh, come on!
We're running late.
If you haven't got
your lip colour on,
can you line up behind Rose,
please?
Have you all been
to the lavatory?
Yes.
I want no running
on the stage.
They're bringing in
extra chairs!
Do not touch the blood.
And look who's here, hmm?
The musical Mr Baines.
Whoa! What are you going to
play for us tonight?
'Twinkle Twinkle', eh, George?
How about a little tinkle,
tinkle, George?
Perhaps you would like
to turn the pages for Nessie.
She's playing for the children.
I'm in costume.
I'm very pleased
you've taken up the piano.
Now, where's this song?
George? Excuse me.
How about
'Mary Had a Little Lamb'?
"Baaaaa!"
Or a polka? Come on, George,
what's it to be, hmm?
Fools.
Come on, George. Move along.
Ladies and gentlemen,
could you take
your seats, please?
We're about to begin.
And so the young maid
came upon each and all
of Bluebeard's missing wives,
their severed heads
still bleeding,
their eyes still crying.
Slow down, Nessie!
Slow down!
But hush!
Who comes?
I'm home early,
my sweet wife!
Where art thou?
Oh, husband! What a surprise!
Yes, wife. A surprise indeed.
So, now you know my secret!
No! No!
You, the youngest...
...and sweetest...
No!
...of all my wives...
...must be prepared to die!
No! No! Wait!
I shall not wait!
No, please!
Bare your neck!
Help! They're mad!
This is the animal
blood. This is the axe, Chief.
Now, I'd like to introduce you.
This is Mrs Williams.
This is Mrs Parsons.
This...
This is Mrs Reid,
this is Miss Palmer
and this is Miss Kerr.
That's very, very nice.
Do what you like.
Play what you like.
I want to lie together
without clothes on.
How many would that be?
Yes.
10 keys.
What o'clock say, Mr Stewart?
Got tupeka, Mr Stewart?
Time for your puff-puff.
Ae. Ae.
Never behave like that.
Never, nowhere.
You're greatly shamed.
You've shamed these trunks.
I know why Mr Baines
can't play the piano.
You missed some here.
She never gives him a turn.
She just plays
what she pleases.
And sometimes
she doesn't play at all.
When's the next lesson?
Tomorrow.
I have given the piano
back to you.
I've had enough.
The arrangement...
...is making you a whore
and me wretched.
I want you to care for me.
But you can't.
It's yours. Leave.
Go on. Go.
Stop right there!
This isn't yours.
What are you doing
with the piano? Hmm?
He's given it to us.
Put that down. Put it down!
You're very cunning, Ada.
I've seen through you.
I'm not going to lose
the land this way.
Stay there!
George don't want to see
nobody. He's sick.
You got the tupeka for Hira?
No.
Much tupeka?
Baines?
Look, Baines.
Baines, look.
I don't think you should have
given up the piano.
I'll make sure that
you're properly taught,
with, you know, music
written on sheets and so on.
I don't want to learn.
You don't want to learn?
No.
Well, what does this do
to our bargain? I mean...
I can't afford the piano,
if you mean me to pay.
No. No payment.
I have given it back.
Well... I'm not sure
that I want it myself.
It was more to your wife
that I gave it.
Oh, I... I see.
Well, I expect
she will appreciate it.
I'm afraid this is all I have.
Hey... bring that back!
Is it alright?
Why don't you play something?
What will I play?
Play a jig.
Do I know any jigs?
Play a song, then.
Why won't she play it?
We get the thing back and...
...she just wanders off.
Well, keep playing.
Wait. Wait!
Why? Why can't I?
I shan't practise
and I don't care!
Blast and damn and bugger her!
Bloody, bloody bugger her!
Let her fall face down
in boiling bloody mud!
Let a spitting mad dog
bite her till she bleeds!
Where's your mother?
Where's she gone?
To hell!
So, what brings you here?
Did you leave something?
Well, I've not found anything.
Does he know something?
The piano was not harmed?
It arrived safely?
Would you like to sit?
I am going to sit.
Ada.
I am unhappy.
Because I... want you.
Because my mind
has seized on you
and can think of nothing else.
This is why I suffer.
I... am sick with longing.
I don't eat. I don't sleep.
So if you've come
with no feeling for me,
then go.
Go.
Get out.
Leave!
What?
Whisper it.
Now you are going,
I am miserable.
Why is that?
Ada, I need to know,
what will you do?
Will you come again?
Wait.
I... don't know
what you're thinking.
Does this mean something
to you? Eh?
I already miss you.
Ada.
Do you love me?
Come tomorrow. If you are
serious, come tomorrow.
Mumma, stay still!
Stay still!
Mumma! Mumma!
They're playing your piano!
Mumma!
Here, Papa.
You shouldn't have gone
up there, should you?
I don't like it
and nor does Papa.
We can play cards if you like.
She's asleep. Look.
One night she was found
in her nightgown
on the road to London.
Grandpa said
her feet were cut so badly,
she couldn't walk for a week.
Ada.
Alisdair, is it
because of our play?
Have the natives aggressed you?
Well, I have to say, you have
done the wrong thing here.
You have put the latch
on the outside, you see?
Now when you close the door,
it will be the Maoris
that lock you in, you see?
With the latch on that side,
you are quite trapped.
Quite trapped.
We have just come
from George Baines's
and they have taken him over.
It is no wonder he is leaving.
He's got in too deep
with the natives.
They sit on his floor as proud
as kings but without...
A shred of manners.
He's quite altered,
as if they have been trying
some native witchcraft on him.
Well, tomorrow or the day
after, he will be gone.
So Baines
is packing up?
Well, he has nothing to pack,
but he is leaving.
And it is just as well.
Nessie has foolishly grown
an affection for him.
We have had some tears.
Stop it. Stop!
Stop!
I'm quite frightened
of the way back.
We must leave in good light.
Will we be safe?
Oh, yes. If you leave now,
I'm sure of it.
Nessie, hold this.
You know, I am thinking
of the piano.
She does not play the piano
as we do, Nessie.
Up. Up!
No, she is a strange creature.
And her playing is strange,
like a mood
that passes into you.
Up!
Now, your playing is plain and
true, and that is what I like.
To have a sound creep inside
you is not at all pleasant.
What's that?
It's a pigeon, Auntie.
I should have waited!
I want to touch you.
Why can't I touch you?
Don't you like me?
Ooh! Ooh! Come on, Lucky.
Who is gonna be my friend?
I'm coming to catch you
for my big oven!
We must... get on.
I've decided to...
trust you to stay here.
You won't see Baines?
Good.
And perhaps with time...
...you might come...to like me.
Stop complaining, I said!
And be quiet.
You'll just have to be naked
until I've finished washing
and drying your clothes.
I don't mind if you're cold.
Be quiet.
No, we're not supposed to
visit him.
What?
You're bad!
Crooked, Mr Stewart.
Crooked.
Mother wanted me
to give this to Mr Baines.
I thought maybe it was not
the proper thing to do.
Shall I open it?
No. Give it to me.
Why?
I trusted you!
I trusted you! I trusted you!
Do you hear?!
Why do you make me do it?
Why do you make me hurt you?
We could be happy!
You have
made me angry! Speak!
You lied to me!
You will answer for this!
Speak or not,
you will answer for this!
Do you love him?!
Do you?!
Is it him you love?
She says noooo!
Mother!
Mumma!
You give this to Baines.
Tell him, if he ever tries
to see her again,
I'll take off another
and another and another.
Mother!
Run!
What has happened?
Hush, hush.
What is it?
You're not to see her
or he'll chop her up!
What happened?
Tell me.
Tell me!
Where is she?
Shh. Quiet down!
Quiet down. Where is she?
He chopped it off!
What did she tell him?
I'm going to crush his skull.
Nooo!
No, no!
He'll chop her up!
You pushed me too hard.
You cannot send love to him.
You cannot do that.
Just... even...
...even to think about it
makes me very angry.
I meant to love you.
I clipped your wing,
that's all.
Are you hot?
Oh, my sweet lovebird.
Are you feeling better?
What?
I look at you...
...at your face.
I've had that face
in my head, hating it,
but now I'm here seeing it...
...there's nothing.
You have your marks.
You look at me through
your eyes. Yes.
You're even afraid of me.
Get up.
Baines...
...has Ada ever spoken to you?
You mean in signs?
No, words.
Have you ever heard words?
No, not words.
You never thought
you heard words?
I heard it here.
I heard a voice...
there in my head.
I watched her lips. They
didn't make the words, but...
...yet the harder I listened...
...the clearer I heard her.
You punished her wrongly.
It was me, my fault.
She said...
..."I am afraid of my will...
"..of what it might do,
it is so strange and strong."
She said...
..."I have to go. Let me go.
"Let Baines take me away.
"Let him try and save me."
I wish her gone.
I wish... you gone.
I want to wake up and...
...and find that this...
was all a dream.
That's what I want.
It's a terrible shock.
Aye, it is.
Poor dear.
No. She needs it.
She must have it.
What did she say?
She said,
"Throw the piano overboard."
It's quite safe.
They are managing it.
She doesn't want it.
She says it's spoiled.
I've been given the key.
I'll have it mended.
Baines.
Please, Ada.
Ple... Ada!
You will regret it. It's your
piano. I want you to have it.
She doesn't want it!
Ada, sit down.
Sit... Sit down!
Throw it over!
Sit down.
Alright, we'll throw it over.
What a death.
What a chance.
What a surprise.
My will has chosen life.
Still, it has had me spooked,
and many others besides.
I teach piano now in Nelson.
George has fashioned me
a metal fingertip.
I'm quite the town freak,
which satisfies.
I am learning to speak.
My sound is still so bad,
I feel ashamed.
Deh, deh...
I practise only when I am alone
and it is dark.
Hah, hah. Kah, kah, kah.
Vah, vah, vah.
Pah, pah...
At night, I think of my piano
in its ocean grave.
And sometimes of myself
floating above it.
Down there, everything is
so still and silent
that it lulls me to sleep.
It is a weird lullaby.
And so it is - it is mine.
There is a silence
where hath been no sound.
There is a silence where
no sound may be,
In the cold grave -
Under the deep, deep sea.